Guide to the Burton Jesse Hendrick Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Burton Jesse Hendrick papers
1880-1970
1917-1949
MS 1980
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
21.5
(44 boxes)
The Burton Jesse Hendrick papers consist of research materials, manuscript drafts, and correspondence related to books later published; news clippings and personal materials consisting of biographical files, estate files, and Yale related materials, 1880-1970.
Hendrick, Burton J. (Burton Jesse), 1870-1949
Biographical / Historical
Burton Jesse Hendrick (1870–1949) was born in New Haven, Connecticut. While attending Yale University, Hendrick was editor of both The Yale Courant and The Yale Literary Magazine. He received his BA in 1895 and his master's in 1897 from Yale. After completing his degree work, Hendrick became editor of the New Haven Morning News. In 1905, after writing for The New York Evening Post and The New York Sun. Hendrick left newspapers and became a "muckraker" writing for McClure's Magazine. His "The Story of Life-Insurance" expose appeared in McClure's in 1906. Following his career at McClure's, Hendrick went to work in 1913 at Walter Hines Page's World's Work magazine as an associate editor. In 1919, Hendrick began writing biographies, when he was the ghostwriter of Ambassador Morgenthau's Story for Henry Morgenthau, Sr.
He won the 1921 Pulitzer Prize for The Victory at Sea which he co-authored with William Sowden Sims, the 1923 Pulitzer Prize for The Life and Letters of Walter H. Page and again in 1929 for The Training of An American. Hendrick wrote the Age of Big Business in 1919, using a series of individual biographies, as an enthusiastic look at the foundation of the corporation in America and the rapid rise of the United States as a world power. After completing the commissioned biography of Andrew Carnegie, Mr. Hendrick turned to writing "group biographies". There is an obvious gap in the later works published by Mr. Hendrick between 1940 and 1946 which is explained by his work on a biography on Andrew Mellon, which was commissioned by the Mellon family, but never published.
At the time of his death, Burton J. Hendrick was working on a biography of Louise Whitfield Carnegie, the wife of Andrew Carnegie.
Custodial History
Gift of Mrs. Martha H. Rusnak, 2012.
Scope and Contents
The Burton Jesse Hendrick papers consist of research materials, manuscript drafts, and correspondence related to books later published; news clippings and personal materials consisting of biographical files, estate files, and Yale related materials, 1880-1970.
Arrangement
The Burton Jesse Hendrick papers are arranged in two series: I. Personal Papers, 1895-1970. II. Professional Files, 1880-1963.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Authors, American; Constitutional history -- United States; Industries -- United States; Pulitzer Prizes; Veterans -- United States; World War, 1914-1918 -- Naval operations; Confederate States of America -- Biography; United States -- Politics and government -- 1783-1865; Biographies (documents); Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889; Gorgas, William Crawford, 1854-1920; Hendrick, Burton J. (Burton Jesse), 1870-1949; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865; Page, Walter Hines, 1855-1918; Rusnak, Martha H., Ms.
- Personal Papers, 1895-1970; Series I
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - 1923-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    - Topical
      - The Century Association, 1927-1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Congratulations on winning the Pulitzer Prize, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Cunard Line (BJH travel), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Duer, Leland B., 1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Dutch Treat Club, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Dwyer, Tracy, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Hendrick, Hobart J., 1938-1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        General
        Includes material on the settlement of Carrie Hendrick's estate and the restructuring of H.B. Ives Company.
      - Letters of condolence and replies, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Morse, John, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Murray, Walter F., 1929 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Welo, Hazel G. -- bills and receipts for typing services, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Estate Records
    - Copyright clearances and issues and bibliography, 1932, 1949-1970 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
    - Correspondence
      Includes legal, business, financial, and miscellaneous material.
      - 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 7-12)
      - 1951-1970 (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
    - Estate holdings, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Funeral expenses, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Income tax data -- tax returns, 1948-1951 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Legal papers related to will, 1949-1951 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Manhattan Storage Warehouse Co., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Permission to publish, 1952-1969 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
    - Probate documents, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Family Photographs
    - Burton Jesse Hendrick, Circa 1942, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Martha Hendrick at 18 months and unidentified family members, Undated (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
      Includes undated negatives of family portraits.
    - Portrait of Viscount Morley of Blackburn, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Topical Files
    - Biographical material, 1933-1962 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Biography -- "Burton J. Hendrick, Historian" by Marilyn A. Johnston, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Birth certificate (copy) and correspondence, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Clippings -- New York Evening Post history, Yale, 1900-1901 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Collected autographs, 1895-1945 (Box 5, Folder 6-8)
    - Financial records, 1932, 1942-1943 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Genealogical notes and correspondence, 1942, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Collected by Bertha Ives Hendrick.
    - Obituaries (BJH), 1949 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Personal memorabilia, 1895-1943 (Box 5, Folder 12-14)
      Includes event and travel ephemera and postcards from Queenstown, U.K.
    - Trip to southern Utah (journal?), Undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Writings and correspondence, 1911-1946 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Yale University Club correspondence, with miscellaneous correspondence, 1922-1949 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Yucatan trip, 1932-1933 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Includes selection of Mexican postcards.
- Professional Files, 1880-1963; Series II
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1891-1963 (Box 7, Folder 1-9)
    - Abbott, L. F. -- book on Theodore Roosevelt, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Allegheny College, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - American Federation of Labor (AFL), 1929 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Atherton, Gertrude, Undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Atlantic Monthly, 1903-1904 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      See also: Sedgwick, Ellery, box 9, folder 14.
    - Author's Club, 1923-1932 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Babcock, J. V., Captain, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Baldwin, Roger S., 1925 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Bishop, William Henry, 1898-1909 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Beers, Henry A., 1898-1922 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Bell, Edward, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - The Bookman, 1925-1926 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Buckner & Landau, Attorneys, Undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Cather, Willa, 1906, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Costain, T. B. -- Saturday Evening Post, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Dole, Nathan H., Circa 1910 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Doubleday, Page & Co., 1927-1928 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Employment references, 1925, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Fan mail, 1940-1948 (Box 8, Folder 19-20)
      Mostly for Lees of Virginia, Lincoln's War Cabinet, and Bulwark of the Republic.
    - Frissell, A. S., 1931 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Graham, Clarice A., 1929 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Hertle, L., 1929 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Holland, John P., invention clippings, 1900-1906 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Houston, C. F., Mrs., 1926 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Inquiry on Walter Page at Johns Hopkins, 1923-1928 (Box 8, Folder 26)
      Gathering material for Training of an American.
    - Kellogg, George Dwight, 1944-1945 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Kennan, George, 1923-1924 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - L. Chaundry, Ltd., 1930 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Le Prince, Miss, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Library of Congress, 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Lichnowsky, Prince, Circa 1930 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - May, Earl Chapin, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Miller, Margaret (Mrs.), 1930, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Moore, Edward S., 1930-1931 (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Morgan, A., 1926 (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - Morley, C., 1923 (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1923-1932, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - New York Public Library, 1931 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Pinero, Arthur Wing, Sir, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Poe, Clarence, 1920-1928 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Poynton, John A., 1926, 1932 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Pulitzer Prize on biography, 1940-1945 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Q, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - R, 1940-1942 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Redmond, J. F., 1925 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Reviews, criticisms, and essays, 1938, 1948, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Rhodes, James F., 1922 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Robinson, Chalfont -- Nassau Club speech, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Romanoff, M. A., 1932-1947 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Sedgwick, Ellery, 1902-1946 (Box 9, Folder 14)
      See also: Atlantic Monthly, box 8, folder 5.
    - Shiler, E. G., Professor -- Johns Hopkins article, 1916-1928 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Sioussat, St. George L. -- Library of Congress request, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Strother, E. French, 1921-1932 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Swope, Herbert B., 1923 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Theobald, Victor, 1927-1928 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - U. S. Junior Naval Reserve, 1924-1926 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - University Club, 1928-1930 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - V, 1941 (Box 9, Folder 22)
      Includes printed copy of "Sayonara" by Robert Hammond Murray.
    - Ward, E. S. P. -- vivisection, 1909 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Welles, G. M. -- Mary Baker Eddy article, 1906-1907 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Wilson, Woodrow, 1913-1925 (Box 9, Folder 25)
      Includes interviews about Wilson with other persons.
    - Wright, Orville, 1917 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Writings, 1922-1942 (Box 9, Folder 27-28)
  - Research files
    - Railroads notes from talk with Hiram Johnson, 1910-1912 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Religion, 1906-1911 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Research from contributors "A-H", 1926 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts and notes, 1902-1946 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous research materials, 1910-1943 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Topical files
    - Bibliography, Undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Book contracts, 1935-1943 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Book jackets, 1923-1946 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Financial, 1928-1941 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Pulitzer Prize Committee -- news clippings, correspondence, notes, and memoranda, 1929-1947 (Box 11, Folder 5-9)
    - Radio panel transcript, 1938 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Rockefeller Center business papers, 1940-1943 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Royalty statements
      - Doubleday, Page and Co., 1919-1928 (Box 11, Folder 12)
      - Doubleday, Doran and Company, 1928-1932 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Tax returns and financial documents, 1926-1931 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Writings
    - The Age of Big Business
      - Correspondence, 1916-1931 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Ambassador Morgenthau's Story
      - Correspondence, 1918-1930 (Box 12, Folder 2)
        Includes correspondence and drafts of speech celebrating the tenth anniversary of the League of Nations.
      - Edited manuscript, Circa 1919 (Box 13)
    - Bulwark of the Republic
      - Financial and copyright records, 1945-1948 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - General correspondence, 1935-1939 (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - News clippings
        - 1937 (Box 14, Folder 3-6)
        - 1937-1938 (Box 15, Folder 1-4)
    - Carnegie, Andrew ( The Life of Andrew Carnegie )
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1926-1941 (Box 16, Folder 1-7)
          Includes some research materials.
        - Abbott, Laurence, 1927-1930 (Box 16, Folder 8)
        - Abbott, William L., 1927-1932 (Box 16, Folder 9)
        - Anderson, E. H. (New York Public Library), 1927-1931 (Box 16, Folder 10)
        - Argyll, Duke of, 1927 (Box 16, Folder 11)
        - Bacheller, Irving, 1927 (Box 16, Folder 12)
        - Baden-Powell, Robert, Sir, 1927 (Box 16, Folder 13)
        - Balentine, Arthur, Mrs., 1927-1928 (Box 16, Folder 14)
          Daughter of Thomas B. Reed.
        - Balfour, Earl, 1927-1932 (Box 16, Folder 15)
        - Balfour of Burleigh, Lord, 1927-1932 (Box 16, Folder 16)
        - Bancroft, Frederic, 1927 (Box 16, Folder 17)
        - Barnes, John, 1930 (Box 16, Folder 18)
        - Barrow, Archibald, 1929-1932 (Box 16, Folder 19)
        - Bartholdt, Richard, 1927-1928 (Box 16, Folder 20)
        - Bassett, A. Tilney, 1927-1930 (Box 16, Folder 21)
        - Beall, Edgar C., Dr., 1928 (Box 16, Folder 22)
        - Bell, Hugh, Sir, 1927 (Box 16, Folder 23)
        - Bernstorff, Count von, 1927 (Box 16, Folder 24)
        - Bertram, James, 1928-1932 (Box 16, Folder 25)
        - Bessemer, Howard F., 1927 (Box 16, Folder 26)
        - Beveridge, Albert J., 1927 (Box 16, Folder 27)
        - Bigelow, Grace, 1927, 1932 (Box 16, Folder 28)
        - Blackburn, W. W., 1927, 1930 (Box 16, Folder 29)
        - Blair, David, 1927, 1932 (Box 17, Folder 1)
        - Borntraeger, Henry, 1930 (Box 17, Folder 2)
        - Brent, George P. (Macmillan Co.), 1932 (Box 17, Folder 3)
        - Bridges, Robert (Scribner's), 1929 (Box 17, Folder 4)
        - Bright, Philip, 1927, 1932 (Box 17, Folder 5)
        - Bryce, E. Marion, Viscountess, 1927, 1932 (Box 17, Folder 6)
        - Buffington, Joseph, Judge, 1927 (Box 17, Folder 7)
        - Burns, John, 1927, 1929 (Box 17, Folder 8)
        - Burr, George Lincoln, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 9)
        - Burton, Theodore E., 1927 (Box 17, Folder 10)
        - Butler, Howard Russell, 1929 (Box 17, Folder 11)
        - Butler, Nicholas M., 1927-1932 (Box 17, Folder 12)
        - Byard, Theodore, 1926-1929 (Box 17, Folder 13)
        - Calderwood, W. L., 1928 (Box 17, Folder 14)
        - Canterbury, Archbishop of, 1926-1927 (Box 17, Folder 15)
        - Carnegie, Claud S., 1926-1928 (Box 17, Folder 16)
        - Carnegie, David, 1927-1928 (Box 17, Folder 17)
        - Carnegie, Louise W. (Mrs. Andrew), 1925-1940 (Box 17, Folder 18)
        - Carnegie Library, University of Pittsburgh, 1929-1931 (Box 17, Folder 19)
        - Carnegie Veteran Association, 1927, 1930 (Box 17, Folder 20)
        - Castle, William R., Jr., 1925-1932 (Box 17, Folder 21)
        - Cecil, Hugh, 1927 (Box 17, Folder 22)
        - Choate, Mabel, 1927 (Box 17, Folder 23)
        - Church, Samuel H., 1926-1932 (Box 17, Folder 24)
        - Clemens, Cyril, 1929 (Box 17, Folder 25)
        - Cortelyou, George B., 1927 (Box 17, Folder 26)
        - Cousins, Robert G., 1927 (Box 17, Folder 27)
        - Crewe, Marquess of, 1924-1929 (Box 17, Folder 28)
        - Crowther, Samuel, 1930-1931 (Box 17, Folder 29)
        - Curry, Grant, 1929, 1931 (Box 17, Folder 30)
        - Cutting, R. Fulton, 1927-1928 (Box 17, Folder 31)
        - Damrosch, Frank and Walter, 1927, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 32)
        - Dennis, Frederic S., Dr., 1929-1932 (Box 17, Folder 33)
        - Depew, Chauncey M., 1927 (Box 17, Folder 34)
        - Dickson, William B., 1927-1930 (Box 17, Folder 35)
        - Dictionary of American Biography, 1927-1930 (Box 17, Folder 36)
        - Dodge, Grace Parish (Mrs. Cleveland), 1927 (Box 17, Folder 37)
        - Doubleday, Duran & Company, 1927-1932 (Box 17, Folder 38)
        - Egan, Martin, 1931 (Box 18, Folder 1)
        - Elgin, Earl of, 1927-1929 (Box 18, Folder 2)
        - Eliot, Charles William, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 3)
        - Eustis, Edith Morton, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 4)
          Daughter of Levi P. Morton.
        - Felkin, Ellen Thorneycroft (Mrs. A. L.), 1927-1928 (Box 18, Folder 5)
          Daughter of Lord Wolverhampton.
        - Fergusson, Adam, Reverend, Undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
        - Finley, John, 1922-1927 (Box 18, Folder 7)
        - Ford, Worthington, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 8)
        - Franks, Robert A., 1927-1932 (Box 18, Folder 9)
        - French, Alice, 1927-1928 (Box 18, Folder 10)
        - Furst, Clyde, 1927-1930 (Box 18, Folder 11)
        - Gage, Cora (Mrs. D. D.), 1930 (Box 18, Folder 12)
        - Gerson, T. Perceval, 1930 (Box 18, Folder 13)
        - Gilder, J. B., Rosamond, and Rodman, 1927-1932 (Box 18, Folder 14)
        - Gladstone, Viscount, 1927-1929 (Box 18, Folder 15)
        - Goodnow, Frank, Dr., 1927 (Box 18, Folder 16)
        - Graham, Norval B., 1929 (Box 18, Folder 17)
        - Greenway, Harriet L. (Mrs. James), 1927-1932 (Box 18, Folder 18)
        - Gretton, Frederick, 1928 (Box 18, Folder 19)
        - Grey, Earl, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 20)
        - Grosvenor, Gilbert, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 21)
        - Hadley, Arthur Twining, 1914, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 22)
        - Hale, Edward E. and Ellen D., 1927 (Box 18, Folder 23)
        - Hale, George E., 1927, 1932 (Box 18, Folder 24)
        - Harcourt, Lady, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 25)
        - Harrison, Godfrey, 1927-1939 (Box 18, Folder 26)
          Son of Frederick Harrison.
        - Harrison, Mary Lord (Mrs. Benjamin), 1927 (Box 18, Folder 27)
        - Herrick, Myron T., 1927 (Box 18, Folder 28)
        - Hewitt, Edward Ringwood, 1927-1932 (Box 18, Folder 29)
        - Hill, David Jayne, 1927, 1932 (Box 18, Folder 30)
        - Hirst, Francis W., 1927-1932 (Box 18, Folder 31)
        - Holland, W. J., Dr., 1920-1932 (Box 18, Folder 32)
        - Holt, Hamilton, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 33)
        - Holt, Henry, 1927-1928 (Box 18, Folder 34)
        - Hornaday, William T., 1927 (Box 18, Folder 35)
        - Howland, Hewitt H., 1927 (Box 18, Folder 36)
        - Hubble, Edwin P., 1931-1932 (Box 18, Folder 37)
        - Ilkeston, Lord, 1928 (Box 18, Folder 38)
        - Irvine, James Colquhoun, 1927-1932 (Box 18, Folder 39)
        - Kennedy, Julian, 1930 (Box 18, Folder 40)
        - Keppel, Frederick P., 1926-1932 (Box 18, Folder 41)
        - King, Agnes (Mrs. Alexander), 1927-1932 (Box 18, Folder 42)
        - King, W. L. Mackenzie, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 43)
        - Lodge, Oliver, Sir, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 44)
        - MacAlister, Donald, Sir (University of Glasgow), 1927-1928 (Box 19, Folder 1)
        - Macara, Charles, Sir, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 2)
        - Magazine of Business, 1928 (Box 19, Folder 3)
        - Marburg, Theodore, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 4)
        - McClellan, George B., 1927 (Box 19, Folder 5)
        - McClure, Philips and Company, 1927-1929 (Box 19, Folder 6)
        - McCormick, S. B. (University of Pittsburgh), 1927 (Box 19, Folder 7)
        - McCormick, W. S., 1927 (Box 19, Folder 8)
        - McElroy, Robert, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 9)
        - McGee, Anita Newcomb, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 10)
        - McKenna, Mrs. Thomas and Elizabeth McKenna Stewart, 1928 (Box 19, Folder 11)
        - Melchers, Carl, 1932 (Box 19, Folder 12)
        - Mellon, Andrew, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 13)
        - Merriam, John C., 1931-1932 (Box 19, Folder 14)
        - Miller, Margaret Carnegie, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 15)
        - Mitchell, Langdon, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 16)
        - Moore, Charles, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 17)
        - Moreland, A. M., 1928 (Box 19, Folder 18)
        - Morley, Guy, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 19)
        - Morrison, Hew, 1927-1931 (Box 19, Folder 20)
        - Murray, Lady, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 21)
        - Nevins, Allen, 1932 (Box 19, Folder 22)
        - Northcliffe, Lord, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 23)
        - O'Connor, T. P., 1927 (Box 19, Folder 24)
        - Paine, Albert B., 1926-1928 (Box 19, Folder 25)
        - Perry, Bliss, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 26)
        - Phipps, Lawrence C., 1927-1931 (Box 19, Folder 27)
        - Preston, Frances F. Cleveland, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 28)
        - Pritchett, Henry S., 1927-1932 (Box 19, Folder 29)
        - Putnam, Herbert, 1932 (Box 19, Folder 30)
        - Reed, Charles A., 1928 (Box 19, Folder 31)
        - Reed, David A., 1927 (Box 19, Folder 32)
        - Reid, Whitelaw, Mrs., 1927 (Box 19, Folder 33)
        - Ritchie, Robert L., Reverend, 1932 (Box 19, Folder 34)
        - Robb, James, 1931-1932 (Box 19, Folder 35)
        - Robbins, Howard and Francis, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 36)
        - Rockefeller, John D., Jr., 1927-1932 (Box 19, Folder 37)
        - Roosevelt, Mrs. Theodore and George, 1927, 1932 (Box 19, Folder 38)
        - Rosebery, Earl of, 1927-1932 (Box 19, Folder 39)
        - Ross, John, Sir, 1927-1931 (Box 19, Folder 40)
        - Rouland, Orlando, 1927-1932 (Box 19, Folder 41)
        - Schwab, Charles, 1928-1932 (Box 19, Folder 42)
        - Scott, James B., Dr., 1927 (Box 19, Folder 43)
        - Shearer, James, 1927-1930 (Box 19, Folder 44)
        - Smith, George Adam, Sir, 1928-1931 (Box 19, Folder 45)
        - Spencer, Herbert, Trustees, 1927, 1932 (Box 19, Folder 46)
        - Spender, J. A., 1927 (Box 19, Folder 47)
          Concerning Andrew Carnegie letters at the British Museum.
        - State Department, U. S., 1927 (Box 19, Folder 48)
        - Stead, Estelle W., 1927, 1932 (Box 19, Folder 49)
        - Stewart, Agnes D. (Mrs. Douglas), 1928-1929 (Box 19, Folder 50)
        - Stone, Melville, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 51)
        - Storey, Samuel, 1929 (Box 19, Folder 52)
        - Strachey, John St. Loe, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 53)
        - Swasey, Eva Ingersoll, 1928 (Box 19, Folder 54)
        - Ter Meulen, Jacob, Dr., 1928-1930 (Box 20, Folder 1)
        - Thin, James, 1928 (Box 20, Folder 2)
        - Thomas, Sidney Gilchrist, 1929-1930 (Box 20, Folder 3)
        - Thwing, Charles F., Dr., 1927-1928 (Box 20, Folder 4)
        - Van Dyke, Henry, Dr., 1932 (Box 20, Folder 5)
        - Van Dyke, John L., 1927, 1932 (Box 20, Folder 6)
        - Villard, Oswald Garrison, 1927 (Box 20, Folder 7)
        - Volwiler, A. T., Prof., 1927 (Box 20, Folder 8)
        - Wadsworth, Mrs. J. W., 1927-1932 (Box 20, Folder 9)
          Daughter of John Hay; letters from her siblings, Clarence Hay and Mrs. Payne Whitney, are also included.
        - Walker, John, 1927-1930 (Box 20, Folder 10)
        - Walls, William, 1928 (Box 20, Folder 11)
        - Walsh, Frank P., 1930 (Box 20, Folder 12)
        - Wellington, Duke of, 1927 (Box 20, Folder 13)
        - Whitridge, Arnold, 1927-1931 (Box 20, Folder 14)
          Concerning the estate of Matthew Arnold; includes letters from others.
        - York, Archbishop of, 1927 (Box 20, Folder 15)
        - Young, Jennie Johns, 1928 (Box 20, Folder 16)
      - Reminiscences and unpublished manuscripts
        - Reminiscences of Andrew Carnegie, 1903-1931 (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
        - "The Lady of Skibo" -- unpublished memoir of Louise Whitfield Carnegie, Undated (Box 21, Folder 3-5)
    - Gorgas, William Crawford ( Biography of William Crawford Gorgas )
      - General correspondence, 1925-1938 (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
    - The Lees of Virginia
      - Correspondence, 1932-1940 (Box 23, Folder 1-6)
        Includes photographs, notes, and reviews.
      - Draft manuscript, chapters 1-15, Undated (Box 24, Folder 1-7)
        No chapter 13.
      - News clippings, 1935 (Box 25, Folder 1-5)
      - Notes, Undated (Box 26, Folder 1-5)
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 27, Folder 1)
        See also: Correspondence, box 23, folder 3.
      - Research material, Circa 1935 (Box 27, Folder 2-6)
        See also: Correspondence, box 23.
    - Lincoln's War Cabinet
      - Correspondence, 1926-1949 (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - Photographs and illustrations, Undated (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - Research materials, 1935-1943, undated (Box 28, Folder 3)